<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RUI: Advancing the Organometallic Chemistry of Octahedral Re6 Clusters Containing Alkynyl Ligands]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>383627.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>383627</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Richter-Addo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>grichter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927528</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the support of the Chemical Synthesis program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Lisa Szczepura of Illinois State University will develop synthetic methodologies for the preparation and study of transition metal cluster complexes containing acetylide-based ligands. The chemistry of the related monometallic transition metal species containing acetylide ligands is quite rich in terms of their structures, reactivity and physical properties making them desirable as precursors in the preparation of reactive catalysts and building blocks in the preparation of extended materials. This project focuses on the synthesis and properties of the related but relatively unexplored multimetallic cluster systems containing acetylides. The potential of the newly synthesized clusters in catalysis applications and in the preparation of hybrid materials will be assessed. This research will be conducted in collaboration with undergraduate and master’s level students. In addition, Dr. Szczepura will work with units across campus to engage with underrepresented students in science with the goal of involving them in the proposed studies.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Under this award, Dr. Szczepura and her team at Illinois State University will explore fundamental aspects of rhenium-based cluster-acetylide chemistry to determine how the unique properties of these cluster cores impact the chemistry of the coordinated acetylide ligands. The main objectives of this proposal include an exploration into the chemistry of Re-based acetylides to determine the nature of these cluster-carbon interactions, the development of synthetic methodologies which link cluster cores together via C-based bridges, and investigations into the electrochemical and photophysical properties of these organometallic cluster complexes. Results from this work have the potential to provide a deeper understanding of the nature of Re-based cluster-carbon interactions. The results obtained from the proposed objectives will advance the fundamental understanding of organometallic hexanuclear octahedral clusters while exploring a new facet of metal acetylide chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400260</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Szczepura</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa F Szczepura</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[lfszcze@IllinoisState.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000139184</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Trustees of Illinois State University]]></Name>
<CityName>NORMAL</CityName>
<ZipCode>617901100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3094382528</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[CAMPUS BOX 1100]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>V6WTL4T5FFJ3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF TRUSTEES OF ILLINOIS STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Trustees of Illinois State University]]></Name>
<CityName>NORMAL</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>617901100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[CAMPUS BOX 1100]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>687800</Code>
<Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~383627</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
