<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Flexible Thermoelectric Devices for Wearable Applications]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaime A. Camelio</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcamelio@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922061</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of light weight power supply prototypes to charge the batteries used in wearable health monitoring devices. The flexible thermoelectric generators will enable uninterrupted and continuous monitoring of health parameters. The adoption of faster, low-energy-input manufacturing methods makes flexible thermoelectric generators (TEG) cost-effective but also scalable for large-scale production. By enabling uninterrupted monitoring of health parameters, TEGs can significantly contribute to improving patient health outcomes and reduction in healthcare costs. In addition, the self-sufficiency provided by TEG-based power supplies can reduce combat weight, minimizes unnecessary movements, and ensures uninterrupted signals for warfighters in defense applications. These factors are critical to their survival probability and overall mission success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of next generation thermoelectric composites characterized by high electrical conductivity and low thermal conductivity. The proposed research is based on the understanding and manipulation of materials at the micro-/nanostructure level. The development of these advanced materials has the potential to revolutionize energy conversion and thermal management technologies. Leveraging the newfound knowledge of materials' electron and phonon transport properties, the proposed research aims to produce high-energy-density flexible thermoelectric generators. In addition, this work takes additive manufacturing to a new level by significantly reducing energy input requirements. Eliminating the need for high-temperature curing will increase the efficiency of manufacturing processes and contribute to energy conservation and sustainability. The efficiency gains and reduced energy consumption brought about by this research will contribute to the advancement of additive manufacturing as a whole.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400221</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deepa</FirstName>
<LastName>Madan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deepa Madan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[deemadan@umbc.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000743482</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland Baltimore County</Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<ZipCode>212500001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4104553140</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 HILLTOP CIR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>RNKYWXURFRL5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND BALTIMORE COUNTY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland Baltimore County]]></Name>
<CityName>BALTIMORE</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212500001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 HILLTOP CIR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
