<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Harnessing the Reactivity of Strained Macrocycles to Access Discrete Carbon Nanostructures]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jon Rainier</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jrainier@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924753</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the support of the Chemical Synthesis Program in the Division of Chemistry, Professor Ramesh Jasti of the University of Oregon is studying the synthesis and fabrication of diverse carbon nanostructures having readily tunable properties. Rooted in the development of synthetic methodology and organic synthesis strategies, the highly uniform structures that result from these experiments will allow the Jasti group to synthesize supramolecular nanostructures having unique and predictable photophysical and electronic properties. The Jasti group’s endeavors hold significant promise for catalyzing advancements across the interdisciplinary domains of chemistry, materials science, biology, and physics. In addition to contributing to the advancement of science, Professor Jasti is enthusiastic about training the next generation of synthetic chemists and nanoscientists. As part of this, he is committed to introducing a diverse range of students to chemistry and science through programs like 'Catalyst' where students from nontraditional backgrounds get involved in hands-on science experiences and get prepared for college and careers in STEM (science, technology, engineering and medicine).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While molecules featuring radially oriented pi-systems have long intrigued scientists, until recently they were theoretical constructs. Advances in synthetic methodology have made these constructs tangible. With the support from this award, Professor Jasti's research group is employing a bottom-up approach to contribute to this area. They will delve deeper into the synthesis of strained carbon nanostructures like novel pi-extended tubular architectures, three-fold symmetric pinwheel structures, and expansive cage-like molecules. The Jasti group’s efforts promise to expand the repertoire of available molecules through the strategic utilization of novel nucleophilic aromatic substitution reactions and strain-promoted cycloaromatization reactions of alkyne-embedded nanohoops. These strategies and methodologies will not only be critical for the synthesis of the targeted structures, but the lessons learned from these studies will likely be applicable to a broader range of problems especially in the realm of polyaromatic hydrocarbons and emerging graphitic materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400147</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Jasti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramesh Jasti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[rjasti@uoregon.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000528990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oregon Eugene]]></Name>
<CityName>EUGENE</CityName>
<ZipCode>974031905</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1776 E 13TH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>Z3FGN9MF92U2</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>Z3FGN9MF92U2</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oregon Eugene]]></Name>
<CityName>EUGENE</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>974031657</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1585 E 13TH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>687800</Code>
<Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~600000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
