<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Supporting Students and Early Career Researchers as Participants in the 12th SNO Conference 2023]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2023</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Sustainable Nanotechnology Organization Conference is a unique yearly event dedicated entirely to promoting sustainable nanotechnology. It brings together experts and young researchers from around the world. For  2023, the conference has two main goals: (1) to share the latest knowledge and (2) to encourage in-depth discussions that can spark fresh ideas about how nanotechnology can help address important challenges in the 21st century, especially those related to the environment and human health. During the conference, seven prominent experts from various fields, including science, engineering, medicine, and agriculture, will deliver keynote speeches. There will also be discussions and presentations about nanotechnology's role in hot topics like climate change, infrastructure, energy, sensors, the bioeconomy, and agriculture. To promote sustainable nanotechnology, the presentations and discussions will also focus on how nanomaterials behave in the environment, and their impact on the environment and human health. This sharing of ideas among experts from different areas of knowledge will help us make the most of nanotechnology's potential while minimizing any unintended problems. In addition to bringing together experts from various fields, the conference is a platform for people at all stages of their careers, from students to accomplished professors, as well as nanotechnology stakeholders from academic institutions, government agencies, and industry. Efforts are being made to make sure that underrepresented groups in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics are well-represented and participate actively. We expect that around 120 students and experienced scholars will attend the conference. Attendees will exchange ideas, form partnerships, and recognize the achievements of leaders in the field. The conference organizers aim to increase access to science and nanotechnology, enhance diversity in science, and create an inclusive culture among researchers and other stakeholders in the area of sustainable nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Sustainable Nanotechnology Organization Conference is exclusively devoted to sustainable nanotechnology, bringing together experts and young researchers from across the nation. The main objectives of the 2023 conference are to (1) showcase current knowledge, and (2) foster in-depth intellectual discussions that can generate novel ideas on how nanotechnology can address the Grand Challenges for Engineering in the 21st century, particularly those related to the health of the environment and humans. There will be seven plenary talks by an outstanding and diverse group of experts from various fields of science, engineering, medicine, and agriculture. In addition, oral technical sessions and poster presentations will focus on the role of nanotechnology in critical topics such as climate change, infrastructure, energy, sensors, bioeconomy, and agriculture. To promote integration of sustainability in the applications of nanotechnology, presentations and discussions will also focus on environmental fate, transport, and exposure as well as human health impacts of nanomaterials. This exchange of ideas by experts from different fields of knowledge will continue to catalyze the realization of the potential of nanotechnology while minimizing unintended consequences. In addition to bringing together experts from different fields, the conference will provide platforms for researchers at all career stages, from undergraduate students to distinguished professors, and nanotechnology enthusiasts from different backgrounds, including academia, government, and industry. Efforts are being made to ensure the conference has solid representation and participation from underrepresented groups in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics. The conference is expected to be attended by about 150 students and more experienced scholars, who will share ideas, develop collaborations, and recognize accomplishments of the leaders in the field.  The conference organizers aim to increase access to science and nanotechnology, enhance diversity in science, and create an inclusive culture among researchers and other stakeholders in the area of sustainable nanotechnology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/14/2023</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/26/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400944</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adeyemi</FirstName>
<LastName>Adeleye</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adeyemi S Adeleye</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[adeyemi.adeleye@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000784180</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/14/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/26/2024</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Olivares Martinez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher Olivares Martinez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[chris.olivares@uci.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000905218</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/26/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>IRVINE</CityName>
<ZipCode>926970001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 ALDRICH HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MJC5FCYQTPE6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>IRVINE</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926970001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 ALDRICH HALL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>47</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA47</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>117900</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>764300</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>768100</Code>
<Text>ENG NNI Special Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~20000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
