<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: MRS F23 - Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2023</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mun Chan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mchan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session as part of the Materials Research Society’s 2023 Fall Meeting in Boston, scheduled for November 29, 2023 provides a unique opportunity for early career professionals and graduate students interested in applying to faculty positions to connect with one another and receive feedback on giving successful interviews and writing research and teaching statements. It also enables recruiters and search committees to identify potential new faculty members. The poster session is organized by The Early Career Professionals Subcommittee (ECPSC) Materials Research Society (MRS). Previous sessions have witnessed participation ranging from 70 to 100 attendees. This year's MRS Fall meeting will commemorate the 5th anniversary of this impactful poster session which further highlights its&lt;br/&gt;intellectual merits and impact within the community. Attendees come from a broad spectrum of materials research subareas, thus providing a means for interdisciplinary communication that will foster new research ideas and collaborations. This award will increase participation in this meeting by defraying the cost of registration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2023</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400679</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sepideh</FirstName>
<LastName>Akhbarifar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sepideh Akhbarifar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sepideha@vsl.cua.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000889764</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/26/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mallory</FirstName>
<LastName>Starr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mallory R Starr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[starr@mrs.org]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000919583</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/26/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Materials Research Society]]></Name>
<CityName>WARRENDALE</CityName>
<ZipCode>150867537</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7247792732</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 KEYSTONE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MFPJGRD1NWE3</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MATERIALS RESEARCH SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Materials Research Society]]></Name>
<CityName>WARRENDALE</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>150867537</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 KEYSTONE DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>171000</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>176200</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session' was held on November 29 during the Materials Research Society (MRS) 2023 Fall Meeting. It facilitated full reimbursement of the registration fee for seven participants, including six early career scholars and one graduate student. Additionally, one participant, an early career scholar, received partial reimbursement. The poster session attracted broad international participation, receiving a total of 104 abstracts. Ultimately, 94 presentations were delivered during the meeting.</p> <p>The primary goal was to facilitate the 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session' at the MRS 2023 Fall Meeting in Boston. This included providing financial support for the registration fees of early career professionals, graduate students, and underrepresented groups. The specific objectives were to foster collaboration, networking opportunities, and promote inclusivity and diversity within the materials science community.</p> <p>Annual poster sessions have continued to provide a vibrant platform for exchanging ideas and connections. Activity Highlights of the 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session' at the MRS 2023 Fall Meeting are as follows:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Engagement and Collaboration:</strong> The poster session provided a vibrant platform for early career professionals and graduate students worldwide to engage and collaborate. The event facilitated active communication and networking, fostering connections that extend beyond the poster session.</li> <li><strong>International Participation:</strong> The session attracted 104 abstract submissions globally, with 94 presented, emphasizing its global impact.</li> <li><strong>Celebration of 5th Anniversary:</strong> The MRS Fall 2023 meeting marked the 5th anniversary of the 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session.' This milestone underscores the session's enduring success and its positive impact on the materials science community over the years.</li> <li><strong>Positive Feedback:</strong> The poster session received consistent positive feedback from both faculty candidates and recruiters. The interactive and dynamic atmosphere provided a great environment for meaningful discussions, resulting in satisfaction among participants.</li> <li><strong>Attendance and Demand:</strong> The event witnessed significant attendance, with previous sessions hosting between 70 to 100 attendees. This year's session continued to be in high demand, further solidifying its reputation as a valuable and sought-after component of the MRS Fall meetings.</li> <li><strong>Inclusive Environment:</strong> The commitment to diversity and inclusion was evident in the active promotion and support for the participation of individuals from underrepresented minority groups. Financial assistance was provided to facilitate the involvement of junior-level minority participants, contributing to the creation of an inclusive and equitable environment.</li> <li><strong>Facilitation of Career Development:</strong> The poster session actively supported early career professionals in their career development, offering guidance on application processes, refining research and teaching statements, and providing a dynamic networking platform. These initiatives contribute to the holistic development of participants, preparing them for success in academia and industry.</li> <li><strong>Alignment with NSF Objectives:</strong> The session's alignment with the research and education objectives of the National Science Foundation's Division of Materials Research (DMR), specifically the Condense Matter Physics Programs (CMP) and Solid State and Materials Chemistry Programs (SSMC), was highlighted. The event actively contributes to advancing materials research and education in various domains within the materials science field.</li> <li><strong>Financial Support Impact:</strong> The financial support from the NSF played a crucial role in ensuring the success of the poster session. It facilitated the broader participation of individuals, particularly from underrepresented backgrounds, enabling a diverse range of voices to contribute to the symposium's success.</li> </ol> <p>These activity highlights collectively showcase the impactful and multifaceted nature of the 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session' at the MRS 2023 Fall Meeting. The event not only met its objectives but exceeded expectations in fostering collaboration, mentorship, and diversity within the materials science community.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>  Last Modified: 03/12/2024<br> Modified by: Mallory&nbsp;R&nbsp;Starr</p></div> <div class="porSideCol" ></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session' was held on November 29 during the Materials Research Society (MRS) 2023 Fall Meeting. It facilitated full reimbursement of the registration fee for seven participants, including six early career scholars and one graduate student. Additionally, one participant, an early career scholar, received partial reimbursement. The poster session attracted broad international participation, receiving a total of 104 abstracts. Ultimately, 94 presentations were delivered during the meeting.   The primary goal was to facilitate the 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session' at the MRS 2023 Fall Meeting in Boston. This included providing financial support for the registration fees of early career professionals, graduate students, and underrepresented groups. The specific objectives were to foster collaboration, networking opportunities, and promote inclusivity and diversity within the materials science community.   Annual poster sessions have continued to provide a vibrant platform for exchanging ideas and connections. Activity Highlights of the 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session' at the MRS 2023 Fall Meeting are as follows:  Engagement and Collaboration: The poster session provided a vibrant platform for early career professionals and graduate students worldwide to engage and collaborate. The event facilitated active communication and networking, fostering connections that extend beyond the poster session. International Participation: The session attracted 104 abstract submissions globally, with 94 presented, emphasizing its global impact. Celebration of 5th Anniversary: The MRS Fall 2023 meeting marked the 5th anniversary of the 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session.' This milestone underscores the session's enduring success and its positive impact on the materials science community over the years. Positive Feedback: The poster session received consistent positive feedback from both faculty candidates and recruiters. The interactive and dynamic atmosphere provided a great environment for meaningful discussions, resulting in satisfaction among participants. Attendance and Demand: The event witnessed significant attendance, with previous sessions hosting between 70 to 100 attendees. This year's session continued to be in high demand, further solidifying its reputation as a valuable and sought-after component of the MRS Fall meetings. Inclusive Environment: The commitment to diversity and inclusion was evident in the active promotion and support for the participation of individuals from underrepresented minority groups. Financial assistance was provided to facilitate the involvement of junior-level minority participants, contributing to the creation of an inclusive and equitable environment. Facilitation of Career Development: The poster session actively supported early career professionals in their career development, offering guidance on application processes, refining research and teaching statements, and providing a dynamic networking platform. These initiatives contribute to the holistic development of participants, preparing them for success in academia and industry. Alignment with NSF Objectives: The session's alignment with the research and education objectives of the National Science Foundation's Division of Materials Research (DMR), specifically the Condense Matter Physics Programs (CMP) and Solid State and Materials Chemistry Programs (SSMC), was highlighted. The event actively contributes to advancing materials research and education in various domains within the materials science field. Financial Support Impact: The financial support from the NSF played a crucial role in ensuring the success of the poster session. It facilitated the broader participation of individuals, particularly from underrepresented backgrounds, enabling a diverse range of voices to contribute to the symposium's success.    These activity highlights collectively showcase the impactful and multifaceted nature of the 'Meet the New Faculty Candidates Poster Session' at the MRS 2023 Fall Meeting. The event not only met its objectives but exceeded expectations in fostering collaboration, mentorship, and diversity within the materials science community.        Last Modified: 03/12/2024       Submitted by: MalloryRStarr]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
