<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Building a Sustainable Transportation Service Technician Education Program]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>350000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EDU</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate for STEM Education</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Davis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdavis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A major shift in the automotive industry to Electric Vehicles (EV) has created a need for skilled technicians both regionally and nationally. This project from Ferris State University will establish an industry aligned associate degree and certificate program that is designed to meet industry needs and SAE International EV Certification standards to prepare students for EV employment. Over the course of the three-year project, a new degree and certificate program will be created and launched enabling students to obtain a workforce credential that will prepare them for success in the rapidly growing EV workforce. The project will use a Business and Industry Leadership Team (BILT) to maintain the industry-driven focus of the degree and certificate.  The new certificate will enable technicians working on conventional automotive technology in the field to return for a two-semester program that will re-skill them to support electric vehicles.  Instructors from Ferris State and other schools in the area will benefit from professional development and certification opportunities in EV service technology.  Students without previous automotive experience will be able to earn stackable credentials and be prepared for an international certification in two semesters and may continue to pursue a four-semester program for a transferable degree. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main goals of the project are to focus on program and curriculum development and improvements and align with the industry verified skills needed for the future EV Technician workforce.  This program also provides a pathway for current technicians in automotive service to update their skill set to meet the growing needs of their employers. Collaboration with the BILT and other institutions will extend the reach of this project farther into the region surrounding Ferris State and potentially increase economic opportunities for the service area.  The project will increase the number of workforce-ready EV technicians, through retraining of existing technicians in EV and educating students who have not been in the field in sustainable transportation technology.  Ferris has a significant number of students from underrepresented and underserved groups as well as a large number of students who are the first in their family to attend college. Strategic partnerships will support the recruitment and retention of underserved and underrepresented students to support a welcoming entry to higher education and the workforce.  This project is funded by the Advanced Technological Education program that focuses on the education of technicians for the advanced-technology fields that drive the Nation's economy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2400719</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Themm</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy Themm</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[jeremythemm@ferris.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000874617</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>English</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick English</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[patrickenglish@ferris.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000876577</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ferris State University (Inc.)]]></Name>
<CityName>BIG RAPIDS</CityName>
<ZipCode>493072747</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2315912100</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1201 S STATE ST]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>F7EQFJDU4495</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FERRIS STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ferris State University (Inc.)]]></Name>
<CityName>BIG RAPIDS</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>493072747</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1201 S STATE ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>741200</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>04002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF STEM Education]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040106</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~350000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
