<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Representation Theory and Symplectic Geometry Inspired by Topological Field Theory]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2027</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Geometric representation theory and symplectic geometry are two subjects of central interest in current mathematics. They draw original inspiration from mathematical physics, often in the form of quantum field theory and specifically the study of its symmetries. This  has been an historically fruitful direction guided by dualities that generalize Fourier theory. The research in this project involves a mix of pursuits, including the development of new tools and the solution  of open problems. A common theme throughout is finding ways to think about intricate geometric systems in elementary combinatorial terms. The research also offers opportunities for students entering these subjects to make significant contributions by applying recent tools and exploring new approaches. Additional activities  include educational and expository writing on related topics, new interactions between researchers in mathematics and physics, and continued investment in public engagement with mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific projects take on central challenges in supersymmetric gauge theory, specifically about phase spaces of gauge fields, their two-dimensional sigma-models, and higher structures on their branes coming from four-dimensional field theory. The main themes are the cocenter of the affine Hecke category and elliptic character sheaves, local Langlands equivalences and relative  Langlands duality, and the topology of Lagrangian skeleta of Weinstein manifolds. The primary goals of the project include an identification of the cocenter of the affine Hecke category with elliptic character sheaves as an instance of automorphic gluing, the application of cyclic symmetries of Langlands parameter spaces to categorical forms of the Langlands classification, and a comparison of polarized Weinstein  manifolds with arboreal spaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401178</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Nadler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David E Nadler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[nadler@math.berkeley.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000193081</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1608 4TH ST STE 201]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GS3YEVSS12N6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1608 4TH ST STE 201]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>126400</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~270000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
