<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: CRM Thematic Program in Geometric Analysis]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Qun Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>qli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927465</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Centre de Recherches Mathematiques (CRM) in Montreal will host a large, semester-long "Thematic Program in Geometric Analysis" from April 15 to June 29, 2024. The scientific activities of this Program will consist of 6 week-long Thematic Workshops, a two-week long Summer School (Seminaire de Mathematiques Superieures SMS), and two Aisenstadt Chairs Lectures. The Program's main theme is Geometric Analysis. This is an important field of mathematics with great impact and applications to many other parts of mathematics and physics, which uses and discovers tools in analysis and partial differential equations to address problems which originate in geometry and physics. This Program will bring together a large number of experts in different facets of geometric analysis, and will attract a large and diverse spectrum of participants from North America and beyond. A major goal of this Program is to expose graduate students and early career mathematicians to the recent developments in this important field of mathematics. This grant will provide financial support for junior US-based mathematicians (graduate students and postdocs), particularly women and members of other under-represented groups, to participate in the Program, by helping cover their travel and lodging expenses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The last few years have seen spectacular progress on a variety of very difficult geometric problems, including the spectacular solution of the Poincare conjecture using Ricci Flow, and the solution of the Kahler-Einstein problem for Fano manifolds. The interplay between nonlinear analysis and geometry has long proved to be extremely fruitful. Generally speaking, problems involving the curvature tensor of a Riemannian or Kahler metric usually translate to nonlinear PDEs, which may present a formidable challenge from the analytic viewpoint, but which often can be attacked using the underlying geometric structure. The broad themes of the 6 Thematic Workshops will be: geometric flows; complex and Kahler geometry; special geometries in dimension 6,7,8; moduli spaces and singularities of geometric objects. The SMS summer school will be on "Flows and Variational Methods in Riemannian and Complex Geometry: Classical and Modern Methods", and will feature 10 mini-courses by well-known experts in the field. The Aisenstadt Chairs will be Simon Brendle and Panagiota Daskalopoulos.The Thematic Program webpage can be found here: https://www.crmath.ca/en/activities/#/type/activity/id/3880&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/04/2023</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401549</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Natasa</FirstName>
<LastName>Sesum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Natasa Sesum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[natasa.sesum@gmail.com]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000154639</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/04/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Valentino</FirstName>
<LastName>Tosatti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Valentino Tosatti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[tosatti@post.harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000544092</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/04/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>NEW BRUNSWICK</CityName>
<ZipCode>089018559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3 RUTGERS PLZ</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>M1LVPE5GLSD9</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Center de Recherches Mathematiques]]></Name>
<CityName>Montreal, Quebec</CityName>
<StateCode/>
<ZipCode>H3T1J4</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2920 Chem de la Tour]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>CA</CountryCode>
<CountryName>Canada</CountryName>
<StateName>RI REQUIRED</StateName>
<CountryFlag>0</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>""</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~48960</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
