<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[EAGER: IMPRESS-U: High-throughput agile interfaces for cell sorting]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maija Kukla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkukla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924940</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This IMPRESS-U project will be jointly supported by NSF, US National Academy of Sciences, and National Science Centre of Poland. The research will be conducted in collaborative partnership that unites the University of Georgia in the U.S.; the Institute for Condensed Matter Physics in Ukraine; and the Medical College, Rzeszow University in Poland. The U.S. portion of this IMPRESS-U project is co-funded by the Office of International Science and Engineering and ENG/CBET program. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 1&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses recently emerged problems of scalable manufacturing of live cells for biomedical use; specifically, the project focuses on high-quality cell sorting and separation. Revolutionary progress in the field of cell therapy was made by adult cell reprogramming to induce pluripotent stem (iPS) cells, which can potentially develop into every cell type and form organs. The target cells with healing properties should be quickly grown in sufficient amounts using affordable methods. It is critical to effectively separate therapeutic cells from potentially dangerous, damaged, or transformed (tumorigenic) cells. All existing antibody-based cell sorting procedures also generate a significant risk for mechanical cell damage and loss. In this project, the researchers aim to develop an alternative transformative, scalable, inexpensive, delicate for the cells, and antibody-free cell sorting method based on the interactions of cells with specially engineered dynamic polymeric materials (smart surfaces). This new method of cell sorting relates directly to the solution of the fundamental problem of sorting microscopic particles based on their surface composition. The synergistic, interdisciplinary, international team will conduct this research by combining unique expertise in chemistry, chemical engineering, materials science, and micromanufacturing. The project research program provides ample opportunities for training a diverse team of science and engineering students and early-career researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to develop new methods for sorting mammalian cells based on their affinity to adsorbents without the use of specific antibodies. These new methods resemble chromatography when the high efficiency of molecular separation is achieved based on a combination of intermolecular forces, which are generally unique for each individual molecule. Chromatography cannot be applied for cell sorting because of the high energy of cell-adsorbent interactions due to an increased contact surface area that results in quasi-irreversible cell adsorption. The researchers propose a high-risk – high-payoff project to develop a method to boost cell desorption using dynamic interfaces of polymer brushes or networks. The force sufficient for cell desorption will be generated by osmosis at the interface that undergoes phase transition in aqueous media. The research team selects the thermo-induced changes in the phase behavior around the lower critical solution temperature (LCST) close to the optimal cell culture temperature. By multiple oscillating cycles for temperatures below and above LCST, one can alternate the polymer material between its swollen and condensed states. The interface design is a nanostructured thin polymer layer made of adhesive static and dynamic thermosensitive patches. The adhesive patches will have a combination of major functional groups providing affinity-based interactions. The dynamic patches will periodically push off cells with a lower affinity to liberate the surface functional groups for the following attachment of the cells with a higher affinity, guiding the system towards affinity-based chemical equilibrium. The interfaces will be engineered based on the combination of atomistic molecular dynamic simulations and coarse-grained modeling. The separation mechanism, its efficiency, and the quality of the discriminated cells will be verified with model cellular mixes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2023</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041, 47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401713</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sergiy</FirstName>
<LastName>Minko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sergiy Minko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[sminko@uga.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000179163</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>NMJHD63STRC5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 E CAMPUS RD RM 409]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096Z</Code>
<Text>COVID-19 Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5998</Code>
<Text>UKRAINE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~300000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
