<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Algebraic Cycles, Motives and Regulators]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is to support US participation in Regulators V, the fifth in a series of international conferences dedicated to the mathematics around the theory of regulators, that will take place June 3-13, 2024, at the University of Pisa. The Regulators conferences are an internationally recognized and well-respected series of conferences on topics surrounding the theory of Regulators, many of which have played a key role in recent breakthroughs in mathematics. The conference will bring together a diverse group of participants at a wide range of career stages, from graduate students to senior professors and provide a supportive environment for giving talks, exchanging ideas, and beginning new collaborations. This has traditionally been a fruitful place for early career researchers in these fields to connect with potential collaborators and mentors at other institutions, working on related topics. This award is mainly to support such participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Regulators play a central role in algebraic geometry and number theory, being the common thread relating algebraic cycles and motives to number theory and arithmetic. They are the central objects appearing in several well-known conjectures relating L-functions and algebraic cycles, including the Birch--Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture, and conjectures of Deligne, Beilinson, and Bloch-Kato relating special values of L-functions of varieties to algebraic cycles and K-theory. The study of these objects have led to the development of related fields including Iwasawa theory, K-theory, and motivic homotopy theory. They also appear in many areas of mathematics outside algebraic geometry and number theory, most notably in mathematical physics. The topics covered at Regulators V are likely to include recent developments in Iwasawa theory and p-adic L-functions, K-theory, motivic homotopy theory, motives and algebraic cycles, hodge theory, microlocal analysis in characteristic p, and special values of L-functions and additional related areas of research including applications to mathematical physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Additional information can be found on the conference website: &lt;br/&gt;http://regulators-v.dm.unipi.it/regulators-v-web.html&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2401025</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deepam</FirstName>
<LastName>Patel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deepam P Patel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[patel471@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000678898</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE # 1100]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE STE 1900]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>126400</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~15000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
