<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Minimally-invasive Patient-specific Intracardiac Implants]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jaime A. Camelio</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcamelio@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922061</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is the development of a transcatheter manufacturing platform. Mass-produced, off-the-shelf medical implants often fail to match the geometric, mechanical, and biological characteristics of human anatomy. Traditional manufacturing techniques typically involve hard materials and are restricted to producing pre-defined devices in a limited range of sizes and shapes. However, human anatomy is composed of soft and delicate tissues displaying a virtually-limitless range of sizes and shapes with complex convexities, concavities, lobes, and trabeculations. This profound patient-device mismatch leads to poorly-fitting implants, sub-optimal treatment outcomes, local tissue damage, impaired healing responses, lengthy pre-procedural workflows, and elevated risk for peri- and post-procedural complications. Successful realization of this vision would represent a paradigm shift in medical manufacturing technology and open the door for better outcomes for patients, providers, and the overall healthcare system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on the development of a manufacturing technology for point-of-care, minimally-invasive, patient-specific implant generation directly inside the human body. The envisioned toolkit leverages technical and conceptual advancements in materials science, additive manufacturing, catheter-based technologies, and implantable devices.  The proposed solution will allow clinicians to deliver, assemble, and stabilize soft biomaterials at the target tissue site. Densely-compacted biopolymeric building blocks are fluidized and delivered via catheter into a distensible biopolymeric encapsulation layer. At the target tissue, the soft building blocks are additively-layered into user-defined 3D shapes that self-heal to match the size and shape of the host anatomy. Finally, the outer encapsulation mesh provides additional stability to support long-term structural integrity and rapid tissue healing and bio-integration. Together, this system could enable bottom-up fabrication of atraumatic, personalized 3D medical implants in deep anatomic locations without any need for invasive surgery or pre-procedural planning and device selection.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2402654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
<LastName>Roche</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ellen Roche</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[eroche@seas.harvard.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000782720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>E2NYLCDML6V1</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>CAMBRIDGE</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
