<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Geometric and Asymptotic Group Theory with Applications 2024]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>22100.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22100</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The conference “Geometric and Asymptotic Group Theory with Applications” will be held in Luminy, France February 5 - 9, 2024. This award provides partial travel support for a group of early career US based mathematicians to attend this conference. The conference has an interdisciplinarity nature, focusing on topics in the intersection of mathematics and computer science. A variety of leading experts working in the relevant fields will present their work. Early career US based participants will also be given the opportunity to give talks and thereby enhance their international profile. The exposure to recent developments in the field and the opportunities to communicate with their colleagues from all over the world is expected to initiate new research collaborations. Conference organizers will devote special efforts to recruit and encourage members of under-represented groups in mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study of infinite groups is a very active area in modern mathematics. A major trend in this area is geometric group theory, which aims at understanding the asymptotic geometry of finitely generated groups. On the other hand, this seemingly geometric approach to infinite groups also has deep connections to the more classical theme of decidability, logic, and algorithmic aspects of group theory, which lie in the intersection of computer science and mathematics. This conference will bring together prominent researchers interested in group theory, but from different sub-fields and viewpoints, some on the geometric side, while others on the algorithmic/computation side, to present their work. The speakers are carefully chosen in order to emphasize connections between different aspects, and to stimulate further collaboration. A wide range of infinite groups of great importance will be discussed during the conference, including cubical groups, hyperbolic groups, automaton groups, automatic groups, Artin groups, Coxeter groups, self-similar groups, non-positively curved groups etc. More information is available on the webpage of the conference at https://conferences.cirm-math.fr/3149.html.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2023</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2403833</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jingyin</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jingyin Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[huang.929@osu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000789214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>DLWBSLWAJWR1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>MN4MDDMN8529</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>COLUMBUS</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1960 KENNY RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~22100</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
