<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: 2024 Midwest ASPB Conference Grant]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9228.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9228</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gerald Schoenknecht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gschoenk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925076</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The 2024 American Society of Plant Biologists (ASPB) Midwestern Section Meeting serves as a crucial platform at the nexus of scientific discovery and practical application, addressing the monumental challenges facing global agriculture. One of the main goals for this meeting is to nurture the next generation of plant scientists. Undergraduate students, graduate students, and postdoctoral researchers, constituting approximately 80% of the attendees, will benefit from mentorship and networking with established experts. It is particularly noteworthy that the meeting will commit to promote diversity by actively involving individuals from underrepresented groups, early career scientists, and first-generation college students. The NSF award is a pivotal component of this initiative. It will be used to provide travel awards to 10 underrepresented or first-generation college students and graduate students, easing the financial burden of attendance. These awards, which encourage participation from diverse backgrounds, align with the broader impact of the meeting, aiming to foster an inclusive and thriving community of plant biologists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The increasing global demand for food production, combined with shifting environmental dynamics and the depletion of natural resources, poses significant challenges to agriculture. Plant biology plays a pivotal role at the crossroads of fundamental scientific exploration and practical applications. Timely dissemination of fundamental discoveries in plant biology is not only important for basic science but also acts as a catalyst for the development of innovative, eco-friendly, and sustainable strategies in crop production and plant-based product manufacturing. The 2024 Midwest ASPB meeting will attract an estimated 300 participants from the 15 Midwest states in the U.S. and two provinces in Canada. This event will encompass oral presentations, poster displays, and panel discussions, functioning as a platform for the presentation of ongoing research across diverse aspects of plant biology. These areas span genome editing and genomics, biotechnology, growth processes, signal transduction, primary and secondary metabolite synthesis, and interactions with both the abiotic and biotic environment. The conference's central mission is to foster dynamic discussions, cultivating an environment that nurtures the emergence of fresh ideas and partnerships. Moreover, it seeks to create a supportive atmosphere conducive to guiding and mentoring emerging scientists, with a particular emphasis on colleagues from underrepresented groups. This gathering is poised to encourage collaboration, inspire innovation, and provide the mentorship necessary for the development of the next generation of plant biologists who can address the pressing challenges of our time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/20/2023</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/20/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2404066</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cankui</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cankui Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ckzhang@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000671584</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/20/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Mickelbart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Mickelbart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[mickelbart@purdue.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000640163</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/20/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE # 1100]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>YRXVL4JYCEF5</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>WEST LAFAYETTE</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479061332</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2550 NORTHWESTERN AVE STE 1900]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>Plant Genome Research Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~9228</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
