<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: The 2024 Joint Research Conference on Statistics in Quality, Industry, and Technology (JRC 2024) - Data Science and Statistics for Industrial Innovation]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tapabrata Maiti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tmaiti@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925307</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This project funds U.S. based student participation in the 2024 Joint Research Conference on Statistics in Quality, Industry and Technology (JRC 2024), which will be held in Waterloo, Ontario, Canada, from June 17-20, 2024, at the University of Waterloo. The organization of this &lt;br/&gt;conference is also in partnership with Virginia Tech. JRC 2024 is a joint meeting of the 29th Spring Research Conference on Statistics &lt;br/&gt;in Industry and Technology (SRC) and the 40th Quality and Productivity Research Conference (QPRC), which happens once every four years.&lt;br/&gt; The theme of JRC 2024 is "Data Science and Statistics for Industrial Innovation." JRC 2024 aims to bring together researchers and&lt;br/&gt; practitioners worldwide who use statistics in quality, technology, and industrial contexts. The conference promotes communication &lt;br/&gt;among researchers and practitioners to enable and ensure the development and widespread use of novel insights and methodology. &lt;br/&gt;JRC 2024 has the potential to benefit society by offering participants the opportunities to gain knowledge and reshape their &lt;br/&gt;perspectives on topics associated with data science, statistics, and machine learning. JRC 2024 will advocate for the ethical &lt;br/&gt;application and understanding of data science, statistics, and machine learning for industrial innovation, which is beneficial for &lt;br/&gt;the long-term competitiveness of the U.S. industry. The conference provides a platform to disseminate knowledge to the broader &lt;br/&gt;community by sharing short course lecture notes, presentation slides, and posters on the conference website. JRC 2024 aims to broaden &lt;br/&gt;the participation of underrepresented groups (i.e., women, racial/ethnic minorities, etc.) in STEM disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;JRC 2024 focuses on recent advancements in methodology, best practices, and innovative applications. Participation in JRC 2024 has the &lt;br/&gt;potential to advance knowledge and understanding of topics related to data science, statistics, and machine learning and how they can &lt;br/&gt;be relevant to industrial innovation. This conference traditionally attracts prominent statisticians, data scientists, quantitative &lt;br/&gt;analysts, and others with an established record of highly influential, methodological, and interdisciplinary research. These individuals &lt;br/&gt;will have the opportunity to discuss the current progress made in statistics and machine learning, such as big data technology, &lt;br/&gt;text modeling, the use of generative artificial intelligence in industrial innovation, and exchange novel ideas and experiences in &lt;br/&gt;working with modern data science to discover knowledge and apply it to numerous fields. JRC 2024 has the potential to disseminate &lt;br/&gt;new methods and data-driven approaches, the evaluation of previous findings, and the validation of theoretical approaches, &lt;br/&gt;stimulate further investigations regarding the benefits of working with statistics and machine learning methods for industry and &lt;br/&gt;increase the awareness of the need to use data science approach in industry. The conference will include three plenary presentations, &lt;br/&gt;18 invited paper sessions, four to six contributed sessions, a poster session, a technical tour, and a one-day short course. &lt;br/&gt;More details on the conference can be found on its web page: &lt;br/&gt;https://uwaterloo.ca/joint-research-conference-statistics-quality-industry-technology/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2404998</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yili</FirstName>
<LastName>Hong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yili Hong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yilihong@vt.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000572125</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240603359</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 TURNER ST NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>QDE5UHE5XD16</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE &amp; STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>M515A1DKXAN8</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240603359</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 TURNER ST NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~12000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
