<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[RAPID: Population Assessment and Sampling of an Invasive Species Wave in Puerto Rico: Apex-Predator Hypercompetition]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2023</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2024</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>122446.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>122446</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leslie J. Rissler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lrissler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924628</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The rapid invasion of three large constrictor species—boa constrictors, reticulated pythons, and ball pythons—into Puerto Rico over the past few decades presents a critical threat to the island's ecosystems. The Caribbean Islands Biodiversity Hotspot, already vulnerable due to global connectivity and climate change, now faces an unprecedented ecological challenge. This research, funded by the Rapid Response Research (RAPID) mechanism, addresses the urgent need to understand the adaptive ecological dynamics of these invaders in real time. The project aims to capture crucial data on the genomes, microbiomes, and pathogens of these large constrictors, informing immediate conservation efforts. This project focuses on sampling source and leading-edge populations of the constrictor species to document potential fungal and viral pathogens, stomach contents, life-history data, and tissue samples for genomic, metagenomic, microbial, and transcriptomic sequencing. Additionally, permanent voucher specimens will be collected for cataloging and monitoring invasion dynamics. Through this project Puerto Rican undergraduate researchers and conservation practitioners will gain valuable training and local community members will be involved in public education on the threats of invasive species.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The invasion dynamics of large constrictors in Puerto Rico impact ecosystems and pose imminent threats to native endangered species, necessitating urgent action. The intellectual merit of this study lies in its unique opportunity to collect data that will allow researchers to understand the evolutionary processes associated with rapid adaptation and niche competition in a three-species invasion scenario. By bridging knowledge gaps in the adaptive potential and pathogen co-evolution of these invaders, the research contributes to a broader understanding of global invasion dynamics. The collected data will provide critical insights into the distribution and diversity of the invaders, known to feed on federally endangered birds, and help in real-time understanding of pathogen threats. The project not only informs conservation strategies for agencies like USFWS, DNRA, and local stakeholders but also emphasizes science education through community engagement, field trips, workshops, and outreach materials. This inclusive approach fosters stewardship for Puerto Rico's biodiversity and provides valuable opportunities for underrepresented undergraduate researchers. In summary, this project stands to contribute significantly to advancing scientific knowledge on invasion dynamics, offering insights applicable to global management strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/04/2023</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2406685</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Colston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy J Colston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[timothy.colston@upr.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000709285</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/04/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez</Name>
<CityName>MAYAGUEZ</CityName>
<ZipCode>006806475</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7878312065</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>259 BLVD ALFONSO VALDES</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>GZRNJ1GZDBM1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>RD8QJEHNYLJ7</ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Puerto Rico Mayaguez]]></Name>
<CityName>MAYAGUEZ</CityName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>006806475</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[259 BLVD ALFONSO VALDES]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PR00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1127</Code>
<Text>Evolutionary Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~122446</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
