<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: The 9th Workshop on Biostatistics and Bioinformatics]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tapabrata Maiti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tmaiti@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925307</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 9th Workshop on Biostatistics and Bioinformatics will be held at Georgia State University,  May 03-05, 2024. It will provide a platform for senior researchers, junior researchers, and graduate students to discuss the latest advances and challenges in the field. The main objective of the workshop is to address emerging challenges in applications of AI, causal inference, and statistical genomics data analysis. The workshop will feature a keynote speaker, leading experts and young researchers, and it provides an invaluable opportunity for graduate students and young researchers to gain experience giving poster presentations. To present posters will help them to receive feedback from experts in the field, and engage in discussions with fellow attendees.  The workshop will provide a distinctive opportunity for collaboration, discussion, and dissemination of ideas.  In addition, the workshop places special emphasis on supporting young people, underrepresented individuals, and women through financial supports, aiming to cultivate an inclusive environment. Through the integration of interactive sessions, networking opportunities, and a commitment to the diversity, the workshop can enhance its overall impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop aims to push the boundaries of biostatistics and bioinformatics through collaborative efforts among various universities. The workshop maintains a very strong program, which includes one keynote speech by a renowned statistician, invited talks by established and emerging experts, poster presentations from junior researchers and graduate students.  The workshop will also offer a short course "Tutorial on Deep Learning and Generative AI" and five Best Student Poster Awards will be announced during the award ceremony. Special effort is dedicated to forging connections with historically black universities in the Metro Atlanta area, by inviting underrepresented individuals to participate in the workshop. We expect that the workshop will attract a significant number of participants from underrepresented groups. Travel support is available for junior researchers, graduate students, and underrepresented people by promoting the inclusivity and diversity within the workshop.  More information about the workshop can be found at the website:  https://math.gsu.edu/yichuan/2024Workshop/index.html.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2409876</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yichuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yichuan Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[yichuan@gsu.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000484331</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<ZipCode>303032921</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4044133570</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[58 EDGEWOOD AVE NE]]></StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[FL 3]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>MNS7B9CVKDN7</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>ATLANTA</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303032921</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[58 EDGEWOOD AVE NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>126900</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~10000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
