<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[Conference: Symposium on Industrial Ecology for Young Professionals]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The Symposium on Industrial Ecology for Young Professionals is organized by the International Society for Industrial Ecology Student Chapter Board under the auspices of the Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) accompanying the Gordon Research Conference (GRC) in Industrial Ecology (IE), taking place May 25-31, 2024 in Les Diablerets, Switzerland. Both this GRS and GRC focus on translating industrial ecology research into tangible outcomes through policy development and implementation. The main goal of this GRS is to provide an opportunity for young US-based professionals who perform research in IE to use their research skills to identify and develop ways to translate environmental engineering and sustainability research concepts into action, discuss their novel research ideas and experiences, and receive constructive feedback. The student chapter community now consists of more than one hundred members, and its board is uniquely suited to achieve goals for the GRS due to a proven track record and robust event planning experience. This GRS aligns with the NSF Environmental Sustainability program goal of promoting sustainable engineered systems that support human well‐being and sustain environmental systems. The goals that the GRS aims to deliver to participants through its programming include: (1) learning how to identify and effectively communicate the intersectionality of research with pertinent and emerging policy initiatives; (2) building skills of argument framing to appeal to cross‐disciplinary audiences including policy makers; and (3) translating research and communication skills into effective research planning and grant writing habits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GRS will provide participants fundamental skills that will assist in research and grant writing, oral presentation, developing effective research products and increasing the impact of their research. It will also provide students and young researchers with the skills to connect their research interests to policy relevant questions. Moreover, it is expected that the GRS will facilitate long‐lasting international relationships and collaboration among young professionals. These collaborations provide opportunity for joint projects that are anticipated to result in benefits to US science and society at large. It is expected that the GRS will have immediate benefits for those US researchers who attend, and compounding benefits for domestic and international environmental sustainability efforts that stem from idea-sharing and collaborative projects over time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/14/2023</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2023</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2409892</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Eckelman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew J Eckelman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[m.eckelman@northeastern.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000072883</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/14/2023</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>HLTMVS2JZBS6</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 HUNTINGTON AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
