<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[I-Corps: Translation Potential of Peptidic Ensembles as Novel Bio-adhesives]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2024</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2025</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>15030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>TIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Dir for Tech, Innovation, &amp; Partnerships</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>TI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Translational Impacts</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Molly Wasko</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mwasko@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924749</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[The broader impact of this I-Corps project is the development of amino acid-based bio-adhesives. Using low-cost and high throughput strategies, this product demonstrates adhesive properties using a key molecule found in mussel foot proteins which allows mussels to adhere strongly to surfaces in seawater. This technology has the potential to impact the biomedical and bioplastic industry, not only in creating a safer product for the users, but also transforming the way bioplastic materials are manufactured using water instead of petroleum-derived organic solvents which are often highly reactive, flammable, and have health hazards. Finally, since the fundamental properties of the material (e.g., surface specific adhesion and viscosity) are tunable, the bio-adhesive can be used on multiple biological surfaces and used for wound healing, dental fillings, and surgical glues.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project utilizes experiential learning coupled with a first-hand investigation of the industry ecosystem to assess the translation potential of the technology. The solution is based on the development of stimuli-responsive peptidic materials and coacervates with modulable internal structure.  Enzyme-responsive peptides can be designed to adhere to cell surfaces and peptides with specific sequences can self-assemble and control the kinetics of enzyme responsiveness. Coupled to this, minimalistic peptides can be designed to control the internal structure of coacervates. In this project, peptidic coacervates and enzyme responsive peptides act as adhesives and plasticizers, respectively. As the source materials are biologically-based, the products benefit from biocompatibility and sustainability. The tunability a water-based adhesive with dynamic internal structure allows potential access to a variety of biological surfaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2024</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2024</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.084</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2409620</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ankit</FirstName>
<LastName>Jain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ankit Jain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress><![CDATA[ankit.jain@brooklyn.cuny.edu]]></EmailAddress>
<NSF_ID>000986925</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/20/2024</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Brooklyn College</Name>
<CityName>BROOKLYN</CityName>
<ZipCode>112102850</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189515622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2900 BEDFORD AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_UEI_NUM>XNAKYW3FTSE1</ORG_UEI_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_UEI_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Brooklyn College]]></Name>
<CityName>BROOKLYN</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112102850</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2900 BEDFORD AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code/>
<Name/>
<APP_SYMB_ID/>
</Appropriation>
<Fund>
<Code>01002425DB</Code>
<Name><![CDATA[NSF RESEARCH & RELATED ACTIVIT]]></Name>
<FUND_SYMB_ID>040100</FUND_SYMB_ID>
</Fund>
<FUND_OBLG>2024~50000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
